<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French herauld sent to the princes of Christendome Printed according to the French copie.</title>
            <title>Herault françois aux princes chrestiens. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838439</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2818</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2818)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 887:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French herauld sent to the princes of Christendome Printed according to the French copie.</title>
                  <title>Herault françois aux princes chrestiens. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Le herault françois aux princes chrestiens.</note>
                  <note>Urging unity against the designs of Spain.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1570-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2818:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2818:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FRENCH HERAVLD SENT TO THE PRINCES OF CHRISTENDOME.</p>
            <p>Printed according to the French Copie. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2818:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2818:2"/>
            <head>THE FRENCH HERAVLD SENT TO THE PRINCES OF CHRISTENDOME.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MY people are fooles</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and ſhall periſh for want of counſell.</hi> Alas who ſeeth not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie fulfilled; who beholdeth not Chriſtendome running headlong into her owne deſtruction, in the meane while, that the enemies thereof ſubſiſt by meanes of their humaine wiſdome, and the Lord vpholding them, who ſhall giue counſell, ſhall it be the Lord? that is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and offended for the wicked life of man.</p>
            <p>Shall the Pope doe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? he is one of the contrarie parties, ſhall we expect it at the hands of wiſe politicians? are not the greateſt part of them, for their owne intreſts, engaged to the one or other ſide? but there is inequaletie amongſt them, (It is true,) but ſuch as is betweene the wolfe and the ſheepe, one ſeekes onely for his owne preſeruation, the other for nothing elſe but to deuoure all. Here I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the bad ſucceſſe of them both, of the wolfe, becauſe God doth not ſend a Lyon out againſt him to teare him in peeces, of the ſheepe, that they doe not kill and eate him vp at vnawares. To giue adviſe vnto them both were a worke of charitie, and thou chriſtianetie the common mother of vs all, open thy bowells, to diſpoſe them vnto peace, hold <hi>Eſau</hi> from killing of his brother, and ſend <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> among his kinſmen, that thou maiſt not be depriued of them both in one day, what wouldeſt thou doe then, poore widdow, being bereft of thy children: Thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2818:3"/> (I aduiſe thee) the miſchiefe which is the cauſe of this. There are three, that is, manners of life, and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, religion and ſtate. The diuell author of ſinne at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in euery nation hath indued ſome to drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which hath drowned all offices of charitie, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned all indeauor and exerciſe of pietie. Others, he hath made ſo ambitious, that they ſeeke all the meanes they can to maintaine their dignitie, ſparing neither God, his ſaints, nor his ſeruice, but employeth them to vphold him: So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Gomora iuſtifie the manners &amp; behauiours of diuers of them. The couetouſnes of others, makes them to forget God, to hide their dealings from men. The wrath of others, moues them to make religion a ſtep to their prophane greatnes: for you are prophane, that haue a great deale of godlines in your mouthes, but deny God in your hearts. Your <hi>Balams</hi> intent is, to make you fall in loue with ſtrange women, and ſo to draw the wrath and puniſhments of God vpon you.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian religion hath brought forth 3 ſiſters, whereof the two laſt are twins, but by men they are called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes, Lutherians, and Calueniſts. The poore and ſmall number of Calueniſts, thinke on nothing els but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend herſelfe againſt the blowes that men ſeeke to giue her, to keepe in the houſe, where ſhe is aſſigned to be, ſhe is eſteemed and held to be a criminall like <hi>Mephibezeth,</hi> ſhe is areſted in Ieruſalem, and there is nether bands of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, mecknes of Spirit, nor law, required of her ſeruitures, that permits her to come out of her houſe of humilitie and ſeruitude, to take place in honorable throanes, to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in good offices, to participate with greatnes (the benefit of our common father,) ſhe dares not ſpeake to her mother but ſecretly, pray vnto God but in the fields, baptiſe her children but out of the townes, to maintaine herſelfe in this deplorable ſtate, what then muſt ſhe doe? ſhee muſt not crie out againſt her ſiſters, ſhee muſt ſuffer herſelfe to be beaten by Kings and Princes, to haue her
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2818:3"/> riches and Iewels taken from her. the (gages of her maſters word) and ſhe muſt not ſpeake one word, for if ſhe doe, her tongue ſhall be cut out, alas poore deſolate woman.</p>
            <p>The Lutherian extendeth her bounds further abroad, ſhe loueth not the Calueniſt; ſhe hate h the Catholike, the one hauing firſt beaten her, the other becauſe ſhe cannot endure to ſee her proſperitie, ſhe is well grounded in the one, &amp; hath nothing but envie of the other, for her fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhe would gadly ſee them both faire buried, to effect this, ſometimes ſhe agreeth with the one, and then againe with the other, to watch them both, attending the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſhake off the yoake of the great one, and to giue the leſſer a blow on the eare, vſeing the cloake of ſtate to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer her maxime of religion; Oh moſt dangerous deceite: but her maske being once puld off, it will cauſe <hi>leſabel</hi> to be throwne out of the window, by him whom thou moſt honoreſt.</p>
            <p>The Catholicke, hath other deſignes, ſhe will ſtrech her wings abroad in all places, ſhe will haue no companion, much leſſe a controler, ſhe muſt driue away the Lutheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for hauing injured her, calling her wife and ſpouſe of Antechriſt, and ſhe muſt puniſh the Calueniſt for calling her an Idolater, and as there is but one paſtor, ſo there is but one flocke of ſheepe, whereof the Pope is auouched to bethe head and guide.</p>
            <p>To effect the ſame he holdeth the good ſheepe tyed faſt to his greatnes, by Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chaine, thoſe that are ſcabby, by the feare of the whip of excommunication, the moſt ſencible by the golden calfe, and all in generall by auricular conſeſſion, greatnes of reuenewes, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of houſes.</p>
            <p>We muſt bring the others vnto vs, they ſay and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aske the Lutherian, what communion will you haue, with a ſiſter, that is of ſo different a humor from you. The Samaritans and the Iewes, are ſome what a kin one vnto the other, come lets vs together build vp Jeruſalem, let us
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2818:4"/> agree together againſt this preſumpteous wench, that will beleeue nothing but her owne reaſons, we promiſe you to let you goe to worſhip in this mountaine, to goe to the Temple of Garezin, truſt our word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we obſerue it well to the Iewes, our common enemies, and why not to you that are our friends, but death is in the kettle, the fleſh is made ready for the banket, we will not make the birds wild before they are in the cage, when we haue taken their armes and legs from them, we will bind them like <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and put out their eyes. Siſter the aduantage that thou ſhalt haue, is, that they will eate thee in the deſart, but keepe thee vntill the end.</p>
            <p>To the Calueniſts? giue not a good word, wee muſt beate her and breake her ribs, and looke on her againe to ſee if ſhe be through dead, if ſhe flies into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> we muſt cut her in peeces by the ſword of the ſtate, if ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tireth into <hi>Germanie,</hi> we muſt perſwade her that ſhe blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed God, and the King, and with <hi>Naboth</hi> ſhe muſt be ſtoned to death by the principalle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the country, by <hi>Ieſabels</hi> commandement. If ſhe flieth into <hi>Swytzerland,</hi> we muſt make her beleeue that ſhe hath carried our gods away, rauiſhed the rights of our houſe, and then they muſt make her returne againe, and ſuffer her to be beaten. Shall ſhe hide herſelfe in the mountaines, ſhall ſhe couer herſelfe with the height of the Alpes, ſhall ſhe alledg her long ſoiourning, her neſt built by her aunceſters, we muſt ſend a bird to murther her with a blow of his bill, and for want thereof come and lodge in the fields. If ſhe goeth into <hi>France,</hi> vnder the ſafegard of that great Monarch, it is an eaſie matter to tell him of his oath, and to propheſie vnto him his damnation, if he ſhould fauour ſo wicked a woman, to threaten him with Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſword, if he doth not vſe Saint <hi>Bartholmews</hi> ſword. If that fiſh chanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to ſwime into the little world of England, we will ſend a knife, out againſt that nouriſhing Father, if he will not haue our keye to open his houſe, we will ſend the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2818:4"/> Fryers Minors, that know how to bring it to paſſe, to conclude, little doue, they will haue thee to poure out thy bloud vpon the Aulter, and to take the wings of the wind to flie into the North. <hi>Dauid,</hi> doe thou withdraw thy ſelfe amongſt the <hi>Philiſtians,</hi> out of the houſe of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, or elſe thou ſhalt neuer haue reſt in Iſraell.</p>
            <p>The State encloſeth all, it is the flying Eagle through all the corners of this houſe, and viſiting all the familie, ſayth, that there is but one God, and that we muſt have but one religion, and one King, my houſe is of long continuance, It hath vpholden the Empire, it hath poſſeſſed the moſt Noble Kingdomes in the world, which beareth the title of Catholicke, and ſhall it not take the effect? what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth it? The <hi>Germains, Ltalians, Frenchmen, Engliſhmen,</hi> and their adherents, then we muſt take away all theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles, that the propheſie may be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Who is heat this day that is ſo ignorant of the affaires of the world, that knoweth not, that the King of Spaine onely pretendeth to make himſelfe ſole Monarch of the world, that it is the proiect wherevpon (all the enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that are made from day to day throughout the world) are grounded, he beleeueth that he hath his right, by the long poſſeſſion of the Empire, by the force of his houſe, the greatnes of his eſtates, the ſubtilty of his counſell, the fidelitie of his people, and his great aboundance of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, he thinkes no man to be a lawfull King but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Germains, Netherlands,</hi> and <hi>Zwitzers,</hi> withdrew themſelues from the Empire by the cowardiſe of ſome Emperors. The Common wealthes haue abuſed their bountie and freedome, hauing a reſpect to other deſignes. The <hi>Frenchmen</hi> are to preſumptious. The <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> by order of decencie ought to doe homage vnto him. The <hi>Sauoiard</hi> ought to bluſh for ſhame, for meaſuring his ſword with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſword. The <hi>Italian</hi> Princes ſhould be to raſh, if they proceed with their deſignes to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2818:5"/> prauaile of his bleſſing, the right of commaunding all men belongeth vnto him.</p>
            <p>If they doe it, euery one of them ſhall peaceably feed vnder his owne fig tree, he is no Tyrant, he asketh no tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, he is content that his titles of honor may be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by adding thereunto Emperour of <hi>Germanie,</hi> King of <hi>France, England, Denmarke, Swethland, Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Hongaria,</hi> he quiteth the kingdome of <hi>Iuitot,</hi> the States, the Common wealthes, the Princes, and the Barons ſhall haue their priuiledges, doing homage vnto him. He is the the moſt mild Prince, his eſtate moſt iuſt and vpright, and people moſt accompliſhed that are in all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>But the diffacultie conſiſteth in bringing the ſame to paſſe, but thus it muſt be done. The Emperor is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Potentate in all Chriſtendome, he is of his houſe, he muſt put downe the Kings of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hongaria,</hi> thoſe two armes which he had bound. <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſhalbe eaſely won by money, that ſhalbe ſowen in that auariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Country, and the honor that ſhalbe promiſed to the principall perſons of the land, the people will follow their trayne betweene both, the rebels ſhallbe puniſhed, their goods confiſcate, wherewith we will pay that which we corruptly promiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Germainy</hi> is full of free Princes and Common wealthes, how ſhall we bridle them, we muſt offer the whip to the Calueniſts Princes, to the Lutherians the purſe, to the Catholike the Popes Bull, ſo then they are ours, if any of them be ſtif and will not bow, examples, diſcourſes, and the ſword, are puiſant arguments to diſpute withall. The <hi>Zwitzers</hi> are vnited in league together, ſo they are, againſt others, to mocke the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> laugh at the <hi>Sauoyans,</hi> and ieſt with all their neighbours, but if we ſay vnto the ſmall Cantons, we will let you liue in your Sates, exalt your condition, giue you the ſpoyle of your fellow Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, aſſiſt you againſt their forces, and Dagon will bleſſe you, to what thing will they not be drawne, they will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2818:5"/> falſefie their faith alliances being caſt into the fire, they will run vnto the pray, as young Eagles run to carrien.</p>
            <p>The Sates haue a ſtrong bulwarke, and in a manner im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable, we muſt not begin that way, we had need of as many Stratagems, as there are graines in a Pomegranat, againſt this <hi>Orange</hi> and his adherents? The Country is like the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> there is ſome deuine protection, that ſemes to impeach the courſe of our Empire, all that is nothing, for a knife will cut his throate, a fig will pierce his intrailes, a Mule laden with gold will win tongues in the Country to ſpeake, hands to ſtrike, and feete to run.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Italie</hi> is ours, if that begin once to ſtirre, we will haue recourſe to our neceſſitie, we will leſſen the money thereof by borrowing, we will require men neuer to ſend them againe, we will employ the holy <hi>Pantofle,</hi> to blow a ſpirit of obedience into their hearts. The Vnion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene our two crownes agrees like the Sunne and the Moone, we will yeald vnto him to haue light in the lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, let him cauſe vs to finde out the Monarchie, after that we will reckon together; and ſhe as the ſtrongeſt, ſhall beare the blowes of our armes.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Sauoye,</hi> will put himſelfe into the ballance to ſerue to make waight, he depends vpon the infernall gods, he lifteth vp his hand againſt vs, but it is but in ieſt, wee will impoſe ſilence vnto him, vpon hope to be our companion in the benefit. Money ſhall raine into his purſe, by the paſſage of our Souldiers, his officers ſhall be faithfull vnto vs, wee will giue him the towne that long time hath bin a thorne in his finger, of Prince of <hi>Piemont,</hi> wee will make him Biſhop and Prince of <hi>Geneua,</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for the ſword and the maſſe, cannot liue together without Scandall.</p>
            <p>The great and puiſant King of <hi>France,</hi> ſemeth to merit ſome thing in our houſe, his perſon and ours are equall, we will neuer remoue our Fathers bounds, our alliances bind vs together, euery one ſhall perticipate in the cake,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2818:6"/> I wil part it take all to my ſelfe, and giue nothing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I will let him deale with the Huguenots, treate of places of ſecuritie, and ſay that they thought not to keep them, to offend him, if they refuſe him, then he ſhall be troubled to take them, ether by force or fraud. If they yeeld them vnto him, it is as much as to take the dogs that were the gardians of the ſheepe, from them. The neceſſetie of great affaires conſtraines the King to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the impreſt mony otherwiſe then for the mainete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of miniſters, there needs but the fourth part, for the principaleſt amongſt them, to keepe them from barking, the reſt dare not blow: we will not touch the libertie of conſcience, we will preſerue the obedient child vnder the benefit of the edicts, we will cauſe the rebels to feele the force of the <hi>French</hi> armes, and the concluſion ſhall be, that will make them agree, to their owne domage.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſhman</hi> withdrawes himſelfe out of the world, can he well eſcape our hands: let him not be perſwaded that it is now as it was in the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> her people loued her, her ſubiects feared her, her courage made her redoubtable, her neighbours receiued great blowes for ſeeking to offend her. This truſteth in our promiſes, beleeueth our words, giues eare vnto our Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, which maketh his eſtate capeable of our domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Thus we haue attained the degree of our intent, and are come to the end of our enterpriſe, long ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected: where vnto the ayde of the moſt puiſant God, and our wiſedome, without doubt will bring vs, reioyce you that are our ſubiects for the greatnes which we prepare for you, euery gentleman ſhall be a prince, in that happy day. You that are vnder other mens Dominons, ſtretch out your armes vnto vs, we will place you in an Aprill, where you ſhall no more feare the heate of the Sunne of warres, in a ſure hauen without feare of Tempeſts, euery one that will not bow vnder this yoake, ſhall be rooted out, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2818:6"/>
            <p>You heare this Thundering voice of <hi>Spaine,</hi> this Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Trumpet, hearken likewiſe vnto me all you peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations, that I may freely giue you my aduiſe. Would you haue the diuell to be your maſter, all of you will ſay, no, then flie from, and ſhun the cauſes that may make you his ſlaues: forſake drunkennes, ambition, couetouſnes, luſt, profanation, and Athiſme, which make your liues abominable, and filthy, and your conuerſation in famous before the iuſt <hi>Lots,</hi> that conuerſe amongſt you as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Sodome.</p>
            <p>Youi Princes obſerue you godlynes, and you that are ſubiects ſubmit your ſelues vnto them, and the great King of Kings will ſhortly tread Sathans head vnder his feete. And you Churches, would you loſe your Sancttu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, and make your candleſticke to be taken out of the place, and your lampe to be put out for euer? by no meanes. Then thou Catholike, content thy ſelfe with thy wide and ſpacious Sea, ſtirre not the ſand becauſe it is ſmale, it is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee for a Herauld ſent by the Soueraigne God, &amp; a bridle to thy chollor, learne and know that the Apoſtles and thy anceſters planted the faith of Chriſt, by the ſword of the Goſpell, and not by the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> ſword, that by good life and conuerſation they conuert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Iewes and Pagans, and did not by fire and ſword take away the liues of ſo many Innocents, which cry for vengeance before the heauenly throane, whoſe bloud ſhall be required at thy hands.</p>
            <p>You Lutherians, haue you loſt your wits and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, to hold with thoſe, that obſerue for a maxime, that they muſt not keepe faith nor troth with Heritickes, are you ignorant of that which they haue done to your Prediceſſors, are you not informed of the treatie made in <hi>France,</hi> in 1572. Among the Griſſons the laſt yeare, and in <hi>Languedoc</hi> not long ſince, doe you not know, that they ſeeke to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you, like as <hi>Dalila</hi> did when ſhe betray <hi>Samſon.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2818:7"/> Haue you forgotten, that we are your bretheren, and your ſelues like <hi>Doeg</hi> to be ſent againſt the anointed of the Lord. Shall you be in the land, will they there pardon you, ſhall not you be dealt withall, as we are, when you ſhall no more haue our ſupport, which ſhould make you conſider, ſaue your ſelues and your Religon, will you caſt your ſelues into the fire, to ſhun the ſmoake? Doe you loue them better that ſeeke to bring you into, and make you drinke of the cup of <hi>Babilon,</hi> then vs, that intreate you by the bowels of our mother, open your eyes, plucke vp your hearts, and with vs weepe and bewaile the miſeries of Ieruſalem, let vs vnite our courages, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the throane of Ieſus Chriſt, againſt the inuaſions of his enemies, let vs loue together by good corriſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whereby wee may cleare our doubts, let vs end our differences, and eſtabliſh a good foundation of our faith, we haue all the principles Common, let not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and ſtubbornes draw and carrie vs away, to refuſe that, which concerneth the ſaluation of vs a'l.</p>
            <p>And thou Caluenniſts, it is thou that haſt moſt to doe, as hauing the greateſt number of enemies, but yet thou muſt labor. Thou haſt but two humaine meanes, the one, that thou obſerue diſtruſt for a maxime, and beleeue nothing (further then thou ſeeſt) that ſhall be propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto thee, ſuffer not thy ſpirit to be ſeaſed, with the feare of euill, no more then with ſecuritie, when there is none, if any man kiſſe thee, looke in his face, to ſee if he be not a <hi>ludas.</hi> If any man ſpeaketh peaceably vnto thee, looke if the ſword be not in <hi>loabs</hi> hand. If thy frends per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thee to yeeld vnto the courſe of the water, looke well about thee to ſee whether the way be not paued with falſe mony, examine the prepoſitions, ſound the perſons that propound them, marke the natures of thoſe that bring them, weigh the ſhaking of that which is paſt, with the gages of preſent promiſes, hold thy ſelfe within the bounds of the Common Law, and demoure not, for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2818:7"/> feare, leaſt one vndermine thee, either at the botome, or on the top of the wall. The other hold faſt, let the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liue with her young ones, ſpare not mens writings, and all ſorts of arguments, interpoſe the authoritie of the God of Iſrael, his ſacred word, the bands of promiſes, to ioyne thoſe peeces together that are furtheſt aſunder, if any one be rotten, to heale him, caſt not thy ſelfe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into death, to ſpare him, expoſe not the reſt into danger. If there be any that will ſay, but what ſhall we doe <hi>Elias?</hi> What a number of enemies are there, let vs yeald to ſaue ourſelues, let vs preſerue our bretheren that are vnder the Wolues pawes: cry out and ſay, alas, I would gladly ſaue both the mother and the child, but I ſee them both in danger, if I ſeeke not to ſaue the one. They promiſe to ſpare the feeble, becauſe that without paine they may ſend them to dine with the dead one morning or other, they will haue nothing to doe but with the <hi>Samons</hi> one of their heads wayes more then fifty others. If God be with vs, who ſhall be againſt vs, will they not ſtretch out their armes vnto vs in this neede? Aboue all things let vs not wake the ſleeping dog, but in the caues, let vs reſiſt thoſe that perſue vs, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did King <hi>Saul,</hi> and let vs fight for our ſoules, God will preſerue them, or giue them vs againe in the happie reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection without being ſeaſed vpon by the wicked Spirit.</p>
            <p>Theſe are great projects, but all the world knowes, that they are ſubtill deuiſes, there is no politician, that hath not long ſince proued them, but what remedie to withſtand them? It can no more be done then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of <hi>Alexander,</hi> or the good ſucceſſe of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines could ever be hindred? here conſcience and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage march equally together. If the counſell be of God, it cannot be avoyded, and let vs beware, that think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reſiſt againſt men, we doe not reſiſt againſt the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of him, that transfereth kingdomes to whom he will. If it be of men, it ſhall be ouerthrowne, and we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2818:8"/> or ſome others ſhall by the arme of the Lord. To take the Nimrod by the necke. If it be of God let vs goe and meete him, to ſubmit our neckes vnder the yoake of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, let vs not onely turne backe without oppoſing our armes againſt thoſe of <hi>leroboam,</hi> the vſurper of the Kingdome: but let vs yeeld vnto the Romans, and by their authoritie preſerue both our liues and our alters, Iſraell was led into captiuitie, leruſalem was deſtroyed, the Temple was broaken downe, her ceremonies left off, and the Arke taken. Let not this pretended <hi>Germaine</hi> Vnion ſeduce vs: truſt not in your houſes and treaſor, your heriticall Nations, beleeue not thoſe that meaſure their courages by the elles of the bulwarkes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, truſt not in that nation, (although it be warlike) which loueth it ſelfe, but like the Gebeonites preuent <hi>loſuaes</hi> ſword, for he is not come, but with commiſſion from the Eternall, that ſayd vnto him, goe, and thou ſhalt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer kingdomes. Oh God, if we had a <hi>leremie,</hi> who would not goe vnto him to know, whether the mouth of the Lord hath ſaid it? If we had a <hi>Samuell,</hi> who would not goe to that Oracle, to ſay, Lord, I will doe all that which thou ſaiſt. The Eternall is King, and we are his people, wee will obay, whom he hath choſen. But we neuer read of any propheſies which threaten vs, with a fift Monarchie, we haue no propheſie that the Spaniard ſhall rayſe the fourth vp againe, and ſwallow vp the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, hath not God ſhewed the contrarie, wherein ſhort time the Spirituall and Temporall heads, haue bin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented in the greateſt points of their hopes.</p>
            <p>He will preſerue nothing but the armes and the hands to hold the rod of his furie, not to ſubiect vs vnto them, but to receiue the puniſhment that we haue deſerued, our fathers neuer taught vs to loſe the libertie, that we may haue from God, but to poſſeſſe it with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, If ſtrength and force faile vs, God is ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for his Iſrael, if he doth puniſh vs for a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2818:8"/> of our ſinnes, by that <hi>Antiachus,</hi> at the laſt he will be appeaſed with his people, how many times was Iſrael ſubiect to the Philiſtians, and how many times did God reſtore them to their libertie againe? he ſold them for their ſinnes, and brought them againe to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions.</p>
            <p>Then knowing not the particuler will of our Maſter, let vs follow the generall with <hi>Dauid,</hi> let vs leaue the Arke with the Tabernacle, that it be not loſt, and let vs pray, weepe, and cry out and ſay, Lord weaken the counſell of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> let vs with <hi>Iacob</hi> fight valiantly, and God will doe all that pleaſeth him, with <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> we will cry out, Lord, we know not what to doe, but our eyes are lifted vp vnto the Lord, with <hi>Heſter,</hi> let vs faſt, let vs goe to the king, if in doing ſo we periſh, we will periſh, as <hi>Zonobie</hi> ſayd to the Emperor <hi>Aurelian,</hi> thou and I may begin warre, but God giueth the victorie, If I ouercome thee, it will be no honor. Therefore let euery man in his calling indeanor puiſantly to reſiſt Tirranous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>Great Princes, you would not for any thing in the world loſe your liberties, and yet you take the courſe to doe it, either for want of courage or counſell. Prince of <hi>Spaine,</hi> thou that haſt extended thy limits euen vnto the place, where God hath ſayd vnto thee, that thou ſhalt not goe no further, goe not againſt the anointed of the Lord: for he hath not ſent thee, thou ſhalt not proſper, the land belongs vnto the Eternall, and he hath diſpoſed of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes at his pleaſure. The fourth Monarchie hath but his bounds, build not vpon the walles of <hi>lerico,</hi> where thy ſonnes ſhall pay the forfeiture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Germanie</hi> Princes, are you bewiched with the reſpect of the image of an Eagle, doe you doubt his clawes, are you afrayd of his bill? D oe you not know that all of you are bretheren, and that if you ſuffer one member of your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2818:9"/> body torne, all the reſt will feele it, and at laſt you ſhall all die in <hi>Slauonia,</hi> preuent petfidrous Treaſons and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyakies, whereof you are accuſed, take away enuie and cowardlines wherewithall men blame you, call baeke your bloud, bid your bones ioyne together to you, and you to them, can your conſciences judge of the equitie of the cauſe by the firſt ſucceſſe? ſtay till the end, and you ſhall know, that the hand of the Lord is for his anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: then be not the laſt to bring backe the king, will your wiſdomes permit you to burie this eſſentiall diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is another thing to be king of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, for the quarrell is not with him, in other qualetie, then the firſt, Will your courages permit, that after ſo notable promiſes, you ſhould turne your backes in the day of battaile? Doth not your natiue country moue you at all; will not his aliances farre extended pricke you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Be all well vnited, for the intereſt of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, your honor, and your duties, hold faſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for your common libertie. Will you ſuffer the Turke, to take part with you vpon neceſſitie, or to eate you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your crueltie? will not God aske an account of you, for the blood which he ſhall ſpill? For the Churches which he ſhall ouerthrow, and for the Moſques which he ſhall erect. Your eyes ſhall ſee it, but he will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to enioy it, his Cimiterre will deſtroy you in a moment. This <hi>Attila</hi> the ſcourge of Chriſtians, will make vs dearely pay for the peace obtayned, at the price of your conſciences and remembrances.</p>
            <p>You <hi>Zwitzer</hi> Bulles, you were feared, Princes and Kings made much of you, you are in danger now to be bitten by them, if you ſeeke not to driue away from you all ſeedes of deuiſion, tie the aple of diſcord to your Cabinet, and bind this maxime as a chaine vnto you, we are all bretheren, let vs reſiſt againſt our common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</p>
            <p>Yov States, whom God hath fauored with ſo much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2818:9"/> good ſucceſſe, that he hath raiſed you vp a valorous <hi>Danid,</hi> to leade forth your battailes: that great God hath put thoſe Townes, and Countries into your hands, which he hath taken from the King of <hi>Canaan,</hi> abhorre the remembrance of his bloudy battailes, that you may not put any truſt in deceauers, eſtabliſh perſons of good qualeties with the puritie of doctrine, baniſh thoſe little conceites of Hiſpanioleſed loue. The double duckets will make you haue double hearts, but ioyne prudence with your inuincible courages, vnite your hearts together, haue reſpect to your aſſemblies, and make account of the puiſant arme of warre for your preſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Italie,</hi> how happy art thou to be alone to thy ſelfe, thou art vndone if thou doſt not ioyne better with thy neighbors, and apprehend the greatnes of him, that hateth thee, and ſo long time hath warred againſt thee, hold on the ſide, that the balance may not fall one the one ſide, and thou on the other ſide of thy dceay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Savoye,</hi> thou art a valiant Prince, his houſe, his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, his alliances, the good will of his people, deſerue not to ſuffer thy ſelfe to be muffled like a beaſt, thou art feared more then loued, thy friends flatter thee, and thine enemies tell thee moſt thereof, feare not fooles, neither harken to the wicked any more, but follow the counſell of thy prediceſſors, ſeeke peace with thy neighbours, and make warre vpon him that ſeekth to giue a blow with his foote againſt thy throane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geneua,</hi> thou that haſt ſo great a part in theſe publike miſchiefes, not for thy greatnes, but for that of thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I will place thee in this raneke, they haue a great ſpight againſt thee, and reſerue thee for a breake all for the great bird, thou needeſt not feare him, I, he will be aſhamed to thinke thereon, vnles it be to giue thee to one of his vaſſaules, but to preuent it, I will tell thee how thou muſt feare the enemies, liue in continuall ciſtruſt, leaſt they make thee riſe before it be day: employ thy friends,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2818:10"/> and good neighbours, forteſie and fill thy ſelfe with good munition, and aboue all things liue in vnitie together, hearken vnto all thoſe that giue thee good aduiſe, and vſe it wiſely, haue an eye to ſome of thy inhabitants, fearing leaſt that vpon ſome occaſion they ſhould ſeeke to win the fauors of their Lord, by the loſſe of your heads.</p>
            <p>Great King Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> if you will ſhun the meanes that your ſcepter may not become ſubiect to him that is your enemie, and be of ſo good a houſe as your Wife, harken not to deceitefull words, you muſt exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate your rebellious ſubiects, for thoſe are the vailaines, that ſtirre you vp againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> and not the Lord, It is the double duckets of <hi>Spaine</hi> that ſpeake, and not the good Counſelors of the late King you Father, thinke vpon making puiſant warre againſt your enemies, that vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with hold your goods, and not againſt your Children, that dayly pray vnto God, for the maintenance of your Crowne, who is it, that with holdeth the <hi>Rauilliac</hi> knife, and the Spaniſh ſword, but the prayers made to God, which thoſe poore Huguenots, and their good friends the faithfull <hi>French</hi> Catholikes poure out before the Throane of him that diſpoſeth of Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>King of <hi>England,</hi> you that haue long hands, cut out the tongues of thoſe flatterers, that exalt you as a god, and onely praiſe your wiſedome, and tell you not the truth, doe you not ſee that <hi>Aegipt</hi> periſheth, becauſe you ſaue vs not, will you be loſt? Wake out of your ſlumber, giua your ſeruant the pen, and take the ſword in hand, to that end you are called of God, make your name to be feared, deface the blame that is layd vpon you (whether it be true or not, I will not ſpeake it) for not helping and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining your owne blood, feare the force of the auncient enemy of your Country, and take heed that for want of exerciſe abroad, you haue not ſome thing to doe at home, deny not (for want of action) that moſt reuerent name of Protector of the Church, which you aſcribe vnto your
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2818:10"/> ſelfe, and not to become ſubiect vnto <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhew your ſelfe to be King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtians excuſe the boldnes of an old man, his gray heares bereaue him of the feare of death, he hath not ſought to offend God, deſpiſe ſigneuries, much leſſe to cauſe bloud to be ſhed, but rather to preuent the ſtorme which he ſeeth comming, and feareth that which is to come, by that which is paſt.</p>
            <p>I beſeech him that was before all beginings, to looke downe from heauen vpon his poore deſolate people, to hearken to their prayers, to clenſe their teares, to draw his hand out of his boſome to ayde his ſeruants, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine peace in his Church, to preſerue the States in their iuſt right, to abate the pride of thoſe, that ſeeke to incroach vpon other mens inheritance, and to giue grace to vs all, to acknowledge the Scepter of his Sonne, to fight vnder his banner againſt Sathan his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and after the victorie to make vs perticipants in the Crowne of Glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
